A Guide to the Richmond Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals 1892-1972
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Richmond Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Archives 1892-1972
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 285
5.2 linear feet
Richmond Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Department by the Executive Directory in August 1990.
Biographical/Historical Information
In February 1883, Mrs. W. Ben Palmer held a meeting in her home for those interested in forming a society for the prevention of cruelty to animals. The following month, an entertainment was given at the old Richmond Theatre (Broad and Seventh streets) to raise funds to finance such a Society. Eight years later, in October 1891, there were finally enough interested persons to organize the Richmond Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals. The organization was incorporated in the City of Richmond in February 1892 and its first elected officers were Dr. Jud B. Wood, President; Mr. S.H. Hawes, first Vice-President; Mr. Joseph Bryan, second Vice-President; Mr. W. Ben Palmer, third Vice-President; Rev. H. Carmichael, fourth Vice-President; Mr. James Lyons, fifth Vice-President; Mr. Ira Mowery, Secretary; Mr. W. Ben Palmer, Treasurer; and MR. A.B. Guigon, Attorney. The first agent was Mr. Emmett C. Taylor, who filled this position until his death in January 1929.
For nearly twenty years the Society struggled to survive with very little money and little outside support. The city of Richmond appropriated $500 a year to help the organization fulfill its goal. These funds, with the contributions of friends and the dues from members, constituted the entire budget for the RSPCA. In 1911, the Society received the good news that it was the sole beneficiary of the estate of Louisa B. Nelle, a relative of Mrs. Palmer's. From 1917 through 1923 the work of the Society foundered, public interest languished and funds were not forthcoming. Plans for a shelter had to be put aside for the time.
In June of 1924, interest was revitalized in the Society and the Charter amended to allow for the opening of a shelter. The first shelter opened in October 1924 and housed over 950 animals in its first year. The Society was fortunate at the same time to be incorporated into the budget of the Richmond Community Fund.
Since this time the work of the Society has increased and become a well-known presence in Richmond. A new shelter was constructed in the 1960s and a cooperative arrangements negotiated with the appropriate city offices in areas where the two overlap.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of reports, statistics, promotional materials, correspondence, blueprints, clippings and miscellaneous items relating to the growth and development of the Richmond Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals. The bulk of the collection concerns the construction of the new shelter on Chamberlayne Avenue in the 1960s, but also includes sporadic annual reports and statistics, presidents reports and laws under investigation for the protection of animals.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged alphabetically by subject and chronological therein.
Organization
The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically therein. The oversize materials are stored separately. The scrapbooks are shelved in the oversize area in chronological order. Photographs have been separated and are located in the University Photograph Collection. The book Dogs as I See Them by Lucy Dawson has been transferred to the Department's book collection.
Contents List
- Annual Reports (Box-folder Folder 1.1)
  1925-1926, 1929, 193?, 1946, 1949-1951, 1953, 1955, 1958-1959, 1962
- Annual Statistics (Box-folder Folder 1.2)
  1923, 1947, 1949-1955, 1963, 1968, 1970
- Appeal 1967 (Box-folder Folder 1.3)
- Appeal 1968 (Box-folder Folder 1.4)
- Appeals, n.d. (Box-folder Folder 1.5)
- By-Laws, n.d. (Box-folder Folder 1.6)
- Cages 1952-1955 (Box-folder Folder 1.7)
- Calf feeder/Shipping Crate 1970 (Box-folder Folder 1.8)
- Charter, n.d. (Box-folder Folder 1.9)
- City Pound Contracts 1943-1955 (Box-folder Folder 1.10)
- Community Council Survey (Richmond Area) 1950-1954 (Box-folder Folder 1.11)
- Court Cases Prosecuted 1967-1968 (Box-folder Folder 1.12)
- Dedication of New Shelter 1963 (Box-folder Folder 1.13)
- Furnace 1953 (Box-folder Folder 1.14)
- Glasgow, Ellen, n.d. (Box-folder Folder 1.15)
- History, n.d. 1942-1972 (Box-folder Folder 1.16)
- House Tour 1962 (Box-folder Folder 1.17)
- House Tour 1963 (Box-folder Folder 1.18)
- Humane Association, n.d. 1946, 1954, 1966 (Box-folder Folder 1.19)
- Kennel Renovation Committee, n.d. 1977-1978 (Box-folder Folder 1.20)
- Laboratory Animals (#2), n.d. 1963-1966 (Box-folder Folder 1.21)
- Laws Concerning Animals, n.d. 1912, 1926, 1935 (Box-folder Folder 1.22)
- Minutes 1954-1955 (Box-folder Folder 1.23)
- Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder Folder 1.24)
- New Shelter (Baskerville and Sons) 1960-1966 (Box-folder Folder 1.25)
- New Shelter Correspondence 1961-1963 (Box-folder Folder 1.26)
- New Shelter Correspondence 1964-1966 (Box-folder Folder 1.27)
- Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Folder 1.28)
- Officers and Directors, n.d. 1894, 1924-1954 (Box-folder Folder 1.29)
- Organizational Survey 1968 (Box-folder Folder 1.30)
- Pal's Page 1965-1966 (Box-folder Folder 1.31)
- Photographs n.d. (Box-folder 1:31b)
- Plan for Joint Operation with City of Richmond, n.d. 1968-1971 (Box-folder Folder 1.32)
- President's Report, n.d. 1953, 1957, 1961 (Box-folder Folder 1.33)
- Program of Service, n.d. (Box-folder Folder 1.34)
- Promotions n.d. (Box-folder Folder 1.35)
- Publications, n.d. 1961, 1967-1968 (Box-folder Folder 1.36)
- Richmond, City of 1957-1963 (Box-folder Folder 1.37)
- Trucks 1957-1966 (Box-folder Folder 1.38)
- Virginia Kennel Club, n.d. 1965 (Box-folder Folder 1.39)
- Wayfarer's News 1960-1969 (Box-folder Folder 1.40)
- Women's League, n.d. 1961-1972 (Box-folder Folder 1.41)
- Scrapbook 1955-1956, overize (Box Box 1)
- Scrapbook 1961-1965, oversize (Box Box 1)
- Scrapbook 1967, oversize (Box Box 2)
- Records 1911-1919, oversize (Box Box 3)
- Scrapbook 1965-1968, oversize (Box Box 3)
- Book of Fines for Cruelty to Animals 1916, oversize (Box Box 4)
- Ledger 1892-1910, oversize (Box Box 5)
- Architectural Plans for new shelter between Jefferson and Adams (9 sets), oversize (Box Box 5)
- Mr. A. Mutt Posters (2 posters), oversize (Box Box 5)
- House Tour Posters 1962-1963, oversize (Box Box 5)